# Dominique Caron

PhD student, McGill University.

Quantitative Biodiversity Lab, Department of Biology
Stewart Biology Building Office N7/19
1205 Dr. Penfield Avenue
Montréal, Québec, Canada H3A 1B1

dominique.caron@mail.mcgill.ca

(+1) 514-433-2947

GitHub - ORCID - Website

#### Profile

I am currently completing my PhD in Laura Pollock's lab at McGill University. My thesis focuses on trait-based modeling of trophic interactions of terrestrial vertebrates and the seasonal movements of birds. I am particularly interested in biogeography, biodiversity modeling, and food web ecology. Through my academic and professional experience, I have developed advanced skills in quantitative analyses (R, Julia, QGIS), data management, and ecological modeling.

#### Education

#### **McGill University**

January 2020 - 2024

PhD in Biology

Université de Montréal

September 2017 - December 2018

MSc in Quantitative and Computational Biology

Université de Montréal

September 2014 - May 2017

BSc in Biological Sciences

**Polytechnique Montréal** 

October 2012 - May 2014

B.Eng. in Civil Engineering (unfinished)

## Experience

<b>Software Developper</b> , Environment and Climate Change Canada	2019 - 2022
Conservation Planning Assistant, Éco-corridors Laurentiens	2019
MSc Research Intern, Poisot Lab, Université de Montréal	2018
Research Assistant Ouranos Inc.	2018
MSc Research Intern, James Lab, Université de Montréal	2017
Field Assistant, Bélanger Lab, TÉLUQ	2017
Technical Assistant for the Collections of Marine	2016
Invertebrates, Institut québécois de la biodiversité (IQBIO)	

## Teaching

Lab Coordinator - Methods in Biology of Organisms, McGill	2023
University.	
Teaching Assistant - Methods in Biology of Organisms, McGill	2021 & 2022
University.	

Teaching Development Fellow - Methods in Biology of Organisms, McGill University.

2020

	Teaching Assistant - Biostatistics I, Université de Montréal.  Tutor - Biostatistics I, Université de Montréal.  Tutor - Biostatistics II, Université de Montréal.	2018 2018 2018
	rutor - biostatistics 11, omversite de Piontreal.	2010
Grants, Honors, and Awards	Writing-Year Award, Department of Biology, McGill University.	2024
	<b>Graduate Research Ehancement and Travel Award</b> , Department of Biology, McGill University.	2023
	<b>QCBS Excellence Award</b> , Quebec Cener for Biodiversity Science, QCBS.	2023
	<b>Best Poster</b> , Gordon Research Conference on Predictive Ecology, GRC.	2023
	<b>Learning and Development Award (LeaDA)</b> , Quebec Center for Biodiversity Science, QCBS.	2020-2022
	Best Short Presentation, QCBS symposium 2020, QCBS.	2020
	<b>Undergraduate Student Research Award</b> , Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada, NSERC.	2017
	<b>Intensive Courses Award</b> , Quebec Center for Biodiversity Science, QCBS.	2017
	<b>Dean's Honour List</b> , Faculty of Arts and Science, Université de Montréal.	2015 - 2017
Publications	Caron, D., Brose, U., Lurgi, M., Blanchet, F., Gravel, D., & Pollock, L. Trait-matching models predict pairwise interactions across regions, not food web properties. Global Ecology and	2024
	Biogeography, 33(4), e13807. Eckert, I., Brown, A., <b>Caron, D.</b> , Riva, F., & Pollock, L. 30×30 biodiversity gains rely on national coordination. Nature Communications, 14(1), 7113.	2023
	Strydom, T., Bouskila, S., Banville, F., Barros, C., <b>Caron, D.</b> , Farrell, M., Fortin, M.J., Mercier, B., Pollock, L., Runghen, R., Dalla Riva, G., & Poisot, T. Graph embedding and transfer learning can help predict potential species interaction networks despite data limitations. Methods in Ecology and Evolution, 14(12), 2917–2930.	2023
	<b>Caron, D.</b> , Maiorano, L., Thuiller, W., & Pollock, L. Addressing the Eltonian shortfall with trait-based interaction models. Ecology Letters, ele.13966.	2022
	Strydom, T., Bouskila, S., Banville, F., Barros, C., <b>Caron, D.</b> , Farrell, M., Fortin, M.J., Hemming, V., Mercier, B., Pollock, L., Runghen, R., Dalla Riva, G., & Poisot, T. Food web reconstruction through phylogenetic transfer of low-rank network representation. Methods in Ecology and Evolution, 13(12), 2838–2849.	2022
	Strydom, T., Catchen, M., Banville, F., <b>Caron, D.</b> , Dansereau, G., Desjardins-Proulx, P., Forero-Muñoz, N., Higino, G., Mercier, B., Gonzalez, A., Gravel, D., Pollock, L., & Poisot, T. A roadmap towards predicting species interaction networks (across space and time). Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London. Series B, Biological Sciences, 376(1837), 20210063.	2021
	<b>Caron, D.</b> , Lessard, V., Wu, Q., & Poisot, T. (2019). [Re] Insect natural enemies as regulating factors. ReScience, 5(1), #1.	2019